A Guide to the Papers of William Homer Wisely, 1913-1982 (bulk 1931-1982)
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of William Homer Wisely 1913-1982 (bulk 1931-1982)
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
12778
This collection consists of ca. 2,600 items (4.5 shelf feet).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The William Hoper Wisely Papers were given to the University of Virginia Library by his widow, Mrs. William H. Wisely, in August 1985.
Biographical/Historical Information
William Homer Wisely (1906-1982) was born in Coulterville, Illinois. He married Hazel A. Steinburg in 1930, and they had two children, Janet Lee and Nancy Ann. Wisely received his B.S. in Engineering from the University of Illinois in 1928 and pursued graduate studies in Civil Engineering there until 1941. Subsequently, he received his doctorate in Engineering from Norwich University (1967). While an undergraduate, he worked as an assistant engineer for the Illinois Walter Survey (1926-1928). After graduation he was hired by the Illinois Department of Public Health (1928-1940) as an assistant sanitary engineer and later became the engineering manager for the Urbana-Champaign Sanitary district (1940-1944). He was the Commissioner of the Ohio River Valley Water Sanitation Commission from 1952-1954.
Wisely was a director, fellow, and honorary member of numerous national and international engineering societies, including the American Society of Civil Engineering (ASCE), the United Engineering Trustees, Inc. (1960-1972), Chi Epsilon, and the World Federation of Engineering Organizations (WFEO), for which he chaired the International Organizing Committee. He was a visiting scholar at the University of Florida from 1972-1978 and a visiting scholar at the University of Virginia from 1978-1982. His professional writings included numerous articles and editorials as well as several monographs, including The American Civil Engineer 1852-1974.
Scope and Content Information
The William Homer Wisely Papers comprise approximately 2,600 items (4.5 shelf feet) and include professional correspondence; drafts of speeches and books; reports, articles and notes relating to environmental conservation, the engineering profession, and urban planning; documents of engineering societies; and pedagogical materials. Various published items found with these materials, both monographs and serials, have been transferred to the University of Virginia Science and Engineering Library (see Appendix).
The majority of Wisely's correspondence concerns the formation of a new world engineering society ultimately known as the World Federation of Engineering Organizations. Also included in the correspondence are comments by his colleagues on the professional literature, including Wisely's own editorials and speeches, and responses to surveys and questionnaires on ethics. Among the writings are speeches and editorials by Wisely and others on the engineering profession, ethics and environmental conservation, as well as copies of the newsletter The Digester and drafts of a book on the history of the ASCE from 1852-1974. A list of Wisely's publications appears in the "Offprints" folder.
The research materials include articles and notes on the High Aswan Dam, ethics, engineering, solid waste management, water pollution control (including documentation of European conferences held in 1954), the population explosion, and urban growth. The teaching materials include lectures and handouts on similar topics.
Organization
The collection is organized into five series. The first of these, Correspondence (1958-1980), is arranged chronologically. Series II, Writings, contains drafts and notes for the American Civil Engineer 1852- 1974, copies of The Digester, a newsletter that Wisely edited, and correspondence related to that publication; offprints of articles and addresses by Wisely; and writings by others, arranged alphabetically by author. Series III, Research Files, includes mainly magazine articles and newspaper clippings. The file on ethics contains ethical canons for various professions and societies. Series IV consists of minutes, pamphlets, and newsletters of various engineering societies. The ASCE material contains editorials by Wisely which are arranged by date. The ASCE correspondence has been removed from this series and placed in Series I. Series V, Teaching Materials, is composed of course outlines, lecture notes, handouts, and exams from courses taught both at the University of Virginia and also the University of Florida.
Headings Wisely assigned to his files have been retained when possible: High Aswan Dam, Ethics, Engineering, Engineering as a Profession, Environmental Conservation-General, Solid Waste Management, Water Pollution Control, Urban Planning, Slums, Case Histories, New Towns, CE 492, ENGR 531, Speech Materials, Editorials, ASCE, ASCE History, Conference of Engineering Societies of Western Europe and the United States of America (EUSEC), Panamerican Federation of Engineering Societies (UPADI), and WFEO. Other headings have been added as necessary to refine the original arrangement.
Contents List
- Series I: Correspondence
  - Correspondence 1958-1980, 2 folders (Box 1)
- Series II: Writings
  - The American Civil Engineer 1852-1974: Chapter I 1974, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - The American Civil Engineer 1852-1974: Chapter II 1974 (Box 2)
  - The American Civil Engineer 1852-1974: Chapter III 1974, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - The American Civil Engineer 1852-1974: Chapter IV 1974 (Box 2)
  - The American Civil Engineer 1852-1974: Chapter V 1974 (Box 3)
  - The American Civil Engineer 1852-1974: Chapter VI 1974, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - The American Civil Engineer 1852-1974: Chapter VII 1974 (Box 3)
  - The American Civil Engineer 1852-1974: Chapter VIII & Appendices 1974 (Box 4)
  - The American Civil Engineer 1852-1974: Miscellaneous Notes 1974 (Box 4)
  - The Digester 1935-1940 (Box 4)
  - The Digester- Correspondence 1935-1940 (Box 4)
  - Speech Material: A-I 1957-1972, n.d. (Box 4)
  - Speech Material: J-P 1964-1978 (Box 5)
  - Speech Material: R-Z, untitled 1968-1980, n.d. (Box 5)
  - Offprints and Reports 1929-1978, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Writings by Others 1961-1974, folder 1 of 2 (Box 6)
  - Writings by Others 1931, 1959-1979, folder 2 of 2 (Box 6)
- Series III: Research Files
  - Aswan High Dam: Articles 1962, 1971-1980, n.d. (Box 6)
  - Aswan High Dam: Correspondence 1971-1972 (Box 6)
  - Aswan High Dam: Printed and Photos 1960, 1969-1970, n.d. (Box 6)
  - Aswan High Dam: Reports 1969-1972, 1978, n.d. (Box 6)
  - Aswan High Dam: Miscellaneous Notes and Research 1970-1976 (Box 6)
  - Research: Engineering as a Profession 1947, 1961-1981, n.d. (Box 7)
  - Research: Engineering Education 1933, 1958, 1965-1971, 1980, n.d. (Box 7)
  - Research: Engineering Licensing 1969-1975 (Box 7)
  - Research: Environmental Conservation General 1959, 1967-1979 (Box 7)
  - Research: Environmental Conservation General - Notes and Clippings 1975-1981 (Box 7)
  - Research: Ethics 1914, 1944-1975, folder 1 of 2 (Box 7)
  - Research: Ethics 1913, 1961-1980, folder 2 of 2 (Box 8)
  - Research: New Towns 1970-1971 (Box 8)
  - Research: Solid Waste Management 1965-1974 (Box 8)
  - Research: Urban Demographics 1969-1974 (Box 8)
  - Research: Urban Planning General 1967-1977 (Box 8)
  - Research: Urban Planning - Case Histories 1969-1971 (Box 8)
  - Research: Urban Planning - Slums 1966-1972 (Box 8)
  - Research: Water Pollution Control 1935-1979 (Box 9)
  - Research: Water Pollution Control - European Trip (England) 1954 (Box 9)
  - Research: Water Pollution Control - European Trip (Germany) 1951-1955 [1967], folders 1-2 of 3 (Box 9)
  - Research: Water Pollution Control - European Trip (Germany) 1951-1955 [1967], folder 3 of 3 (Box 10)
  - Research: Water Pollution Control - European Trip Correspondence 1954-1955 (Box 10)
  - Research: Miscellaneous Clippings 1968-1979 (Box 10)
- Series IV: Engineering Societies
  - American Academy of Environmental Engineers (AAEE) 1971-1981 (Box 10)
  - American Society of Civil Engineers (ASCE) - General Records 1950-1980 (Box 11)
  - ASCE - Board of Direction Minutes 1932-1973 (Box 11)
  - ASCE - Speeches and Reports 1961-1972, n.d. (Box 11)
  - ASCE - Writings by Wisely 1957-1982 (Box 11)
  - The Conference of Engineering Societies of Western Europe and the United States of America (EUSEC) 1957-1969 (Box 12)
  - Federation européene d'associations nationales d'ingenieurs (FEANI) 1964-1966 (Box 12)
  - Institucion de Ingenieria Interamericana, S.A. (Anonymous Society) (I.I.I., S.A.) 1968-1971 (Box 12)
  - International Conference of Engineering Organizations (ICEO) 1967-1968 (Box 12)
  - International Conference of Engineering Societies (ICES) 1966-1967, n.d. (Box 12)
  - Union Panamericana de Asociaciones de Ingenieros (UPADI) 1966-1971 (Box 12)
  - World Federation of Engineering Organizations (WFEO) 1966-1976, n.d. (Box 12)
  - Engineering Societies: Miscellaneous 1939, 1956-1979, n.d. (Box 13)
- Series V: Teaching Materials
  - Teaching Materials: CE 492 1975-1978, n.d., 2 folders (Box 13)
  - Teaching Materials: CE 530 1978, n.d. (Box 13)
  - Teaching Materials: EGC 400 (Ethics, University of Florida) 1976-1977 (Box 13)
  - Teaching Materials: ENGR 351 1979-1981, n.d. (Box 14)
  - Teaching Materials: Miscellaneous 1977-1981 (Box 14)